University Photograph; Collection ua390
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Photograph Collection
1847-2005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua390
4,347 items
31.66 cubic ft.
This artificial collection documents the history of the University at Albany, SUNY and its predecessors through photographs and moving images. Images often depict the school's campus, university events, students, or faculty and staff.
Access
This collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These records were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany.
Arrangement
Items within this collection have been organized into three series. Items within the first series, which has been digitized, have been ordered alphabetically by subject. The second series is made up of additional photographs in the collection that have not been digitized. The third series is made up of audiovisual materials produced to document events held on campus.
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of photographic prints, slides, contact sheets, and other pre-digital photographic materials as well as digitized photographs. The materials in this collection were artifically assembled by the University Archives to provide a visual documentation of the University's history.
Photographs; Higher Education--New York (State); UAlbany Reference Collections
- A black and white photograph of a colored etching entitled "Albany" of the city as viewed from Rensselaer with the Hudson River in the foreground. The engraving is attributed to W.H. Bartlet and C. Cousen., ca. 1845
- State Normal School diploma ("certificate") of George H. Dunham from September 16, 1847, signed by Principal David P. Page, Professor George R. Perkins, and Executive Committee Members Alonzo Potter, Gideon Hawley, Harmanus Bleeker, and William Campbell. Photograph reproduction from University Archives., 1847 September 16
- A photograph of a painted portrait of David Perkins Page, founding Prinicipal of the State Normal School, serving from December 13, 1844-January 1, 1848.
- A digital reproduction of a letter sent to George R. Perkins (principal of the New York State Normal School, January 1, 1848-July 8, 1852) by Charles R. Coburn of Owego, NY on March 21, 1848. The letter reads: Dear Friend, I am requested by the trustees of the school in this village to write to you to see if you have a pupil that will graduate this spring that you can recommend for this school. It is the school that I have taught some time. We want a superior teacher or none. We must have an [sic] man of experience, good disciplinarian, apt to teach, willing to keep up with the real improvements of the day, good moral character if pious all the better. The wages will be about $30 for the first 3 months and if good satisfaction is given they will be raised to $35 per month and board himself. If you have a teacher that will answer our purpose please to write to me without delay. Give my respects to Miss Chichester and tell her that her friends are well. I am at presently engaged in the Owego Academy. Yours with respect and etc. Charles R. Coburn, 1848 March 21
- A digital reproduction of the exterior of a letter sent to George R. Perkins (principal of the New York State Normal School, January 1, 1848-July 8, 1852) by Charles R. Coburn of Owego, NY on March 21, 1848. The letter's text is also available., 1848 March 21
- A group portrait of members of the New York State Normal School faculty, circa 1850. George R. Perkins (front row, center) was the first faculty member hired in 1844, the year the school was founded, and was principal of the school from 1848 to 1852. Also pictured are: Silas Bowen; Truman H. Bowen; Darwin G. Eaton; Elizabeth Hance; Frederick S. Jewell; William Phelps; and Sumner C. Webb.
- A portrait of Truman Daniel Cameron, New York State Normal School, Class of 1851. A reproduction of the original daguerreotype.
- A portrait of David H. Cochrane, A.M., Ph.D., Principal of the (New York) State Normal School from February 25, 1856-December [2?], 1864. In the bottom margin is the caption, "DAVID H. COCHRANE, Principal 1856-1864."
- A portrait of David H. Cochrane, A.M., Ph.D., Principal of the New York State Normal School from February 25, 1856-December 1864.
- 1860 portrait of Normal School Alumnus Thomas Barrich. Reproduced from D.H. Cochrane's autograph book, dated June 28, 1860. Barrick led African American troops during the Civil War.
- A portrait of David H. Cochrane, A.M., Ph.D., Principal of the New York State Normal School from February 25, 1856 - December 1864., 1860
- 1860 portrait of Normal School Alumnus J. Oscar Blakely. Taken from D.H. Cochrane's autograph book, dated June 28, 1860. Blakely led African American troops during the Civil War.
- Faculty member Albert N. Husted in his military uniform. Husted was a Captain in the Union Army during the Civil War. Duplicate of 4766., 1861
- 1862 portrait of Normal School alumnus Andress Hull. Reproduced from Flora Gaskill Nye's autograph book. Hull led African American troops during the Civil War.
- A portrait of Joseph Alden, President of the New York State Normal School from April 3, 1867 until May 23, 1882; duplicate of 6125 and 4890. There are crop marks on the photograph., 1862
- A portrait of Emma E. Jarvis, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. On the reverse is photograph 20038, a portrait of M. E. Towsend, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. Written on the original is "Emma E. Jarvis, Class of 1863" and "6154, Students from way back when, class picture 1800's."
- A portrait of an unidenditified male student associated with the New York State Normal School. On the reverse is photo # 6150., 1863
- A portrait of an unidenditified male student associated with the New York State Normal School. On the reverse is image # 6152., 1863
- Joseph B. Fryer, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. Written in the top margin is "Joseph B. Fryer Class of 1863." Written in the bottom margin and crossed out is "Students (from way back when) pictures (both sides)." On the reverse is photo # 20041.
- A portrait of M. E. Towsend, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. On the reverse is photograph 6154, a portrait of Emma E. Jarvis, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. Written on the original is "M.E. Townsend Class of 1863" and "#20038."
- A portrait of John D. Conley, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. On the reverse is image # 20042.
- Marthaette Moak, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. Written in the margins is "Marthaette Moak, Class of 1863," and "Students from way back when, class portraits, 6157." On the reverse is photograph 20040, a portrait of Sophia E. Young, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863.
- A portrait of Eliza Skinner, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. On the reverse is pieces of a portrait of an unidentified woman. Written on the original is "Eliza Skinner, class of 1863," "students from way back when, 6158, class portrait," and "Skinner."
- A portrait of Sophia E. Young, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863. Written in the margins of the original is "#20040" and "Sophia E. Young, Class of 1863," and "Young." On the reverse is photograph 6157, a portrait of Marthaette Moak, New York State Normal School, Class of 1863.
- Orders from U.S.A. General Hospital in Frederick, Maryland, dated July 25, 1865, dismissing Phoebe Barnard, Class of 1847, from nursing service.
- Kate Stoneman, Class of 1866, and later teacher of penmanship at the New York State Normal College. In 1886, Stoneman is admitted to the New York State bar after successfully lobbying the Legislature and the Governor to have women admitted to the bar. She later became the first female lawyer in New York. In 1898, while still teaching at NYS Normal College, Stoneman becomes first women to earn a law degree from Albany Law School.
- A portrait of Sarah Celinda Avery, New York State Normal School, Class of 1867.
- Portrait of Joseph Alden, President of the New York State Normal School from April 3, 1867 until May 23, 1882; duplicate of 3352., 1870
- A portrait of Joseph Alden, President of the New York State Normal School from April 3, 1867 until May 23, 1882; duplicate of 4737., 1870
- A portrait of Sarah Celinda Avery, New York State Normal School, Class of 1867, as a teacher in Gloversville, New York in 1870.
- A Carte de visites portrait of Emily A. Taylor, teacher of Elocution and Ethics at the New York State Normal School from October 14, 1867 until July 2, 1873., 1870 January 6
- Mary Sherwood. See M.W. Diefendorf album in Archives Memorabilia, neg. in Class of 1874 folder. Sherwood became a doctor.
- Portrait of Alice Murray, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of C. Riverius Stiles, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- A picture of Frone Whitney Knapp, State Normal School, Class of 1876, standing outside of an unidentified building.
- Portrait of Belle Dunham, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of George Knapp, husband of Frone Whitney Knapp., 1876
- Portrait of Frone J. Whitney (Mrs. George M. Knapp), State Normal School, Class of 1876.
- A portrait of Frone J. Whitney (Mrs. George M. Knapp), State Normal School, Class of 1876. The portrait has the information "Bowman Northville, N.Y." in the bottom border, which may have been the photography studio that produced the portrait.
- A portrait of Frone J. Whitney (Mrs. George M. Knapp), State Normal School, Class of 1876. The portrait is attributed to J.L. Abbott, who also was known as Jordan H. Abbott and J.H. Abbott. He was first noted as a daguerreian in Hamilton, N.Y. (Madison County).
- Portrait of Mattie A. Cass, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Lisbeth Lindsley, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Clara Peterson, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Mary Willets, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Emma Wood, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Levi Carey, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Lafayette Carr, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Stephen S. Day, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of William De Golia, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of John Graham, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Lindsey Green, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of john Y. McGay, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Frank Noyer, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of O. Jay Wilsey, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Anna F. Field, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Mary chambers, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Martha Colwell, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Emma W. Davison, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Carrie A. Chapin, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Matilda W. Fling, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Lizzie Graves, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Amelia Griffin, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Anna Ladd, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Lizzie Lindsley, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Mary J. Richtmyer, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of J. Wilhemine Weeks, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of State Normal School faculty member professor Joseph St. John., 1876
- Portrait of William De Golia, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of DeWitt C. Dominick, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Charles E. Abraham, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Riley M. Pitcher, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of A. Elting Thompson, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Hiram B. Wilkes, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Dexter Snyder, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of an unidentified student from the State Normal School, class of 1876.
- Portrait of Mary Willets, State Normal School, class of 1876.
- A portrait of Sensaburo Kodzu, New York State Normal School, Class of 1877, who was the first international student to attend the New York State Normal School. Kodzu became a leader of the normal school movement in Japan. A photographer's stamp for Horton, Albany, N.Y. is located in the bottom margin of the photograph.
- A portrait of Sensaburo Kodzu, New York State Normal School, Class of 1877, who was the first international student to attend the New York State Normal School. Kodzu became a leader of the normal school movement in Japan. A photographer's stamp for Horton, Albany, N.Y. is located in the bottom margin of the photograph. A reproduction of 10107.
- A group portrait of students from the New York State Normal School, Class of 1880 on the steps of the school's Lodge Street Building.
- A portrait of Joseph Alden, President of the New York State Normal School from April 3, 1867 until May 23, 1882.
- Group photograph of the Junior Social Club. Anne Pierce from the class of 1884 is in the center of the top row., 1883
- Group photograph of the class of 1884 (June 26, 1884 Graduation)as juniors in front of the Lodge Street Building., 1883
- A portrait of Hannah A. Stymus, New York State Normal School, Class of 1883. A photographer's stamp for McDonald & Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original.
- A portrait of George K. Smith, New York State Normal School, Class of 1884.
- A portrait of Ida M. Isdell, New York State Normal School, Class of 1884.
- A group portrait of Edith Bodley, New York State Normal School, Class of 1886, Ellen J. Pearne, and Anna E. Pierce, New York State Normal School, Class of 1884. Written on the image is "Edith Bodley Ellen J. Pearne A.E. Pierce." In the right margin is the photographer's stamp, "Brown" and "Albany, N.Y.", 1885
- Unidentified female students of the New York State Normal School boarders at 81 Elm Street., 1886
- A portrait of Libbie A. Baker, New York State Normal College, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "Veeder, Albany, N.Y.", is in the bottom margin of the photograph.
- A portrait of Agnes R. Bunton, who attended the New York State Normal School with the Class of 1887, but is not among the list of graduates.
- A portrait of Anna R. Kelly, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. Written in the top margin is "Anna R. Kelly- Castleton, NY."
- A portrait of Hattie E. Wilman, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Emma J. Hill, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "C.A. Howe, 480 Broadway, Albany, N.Y.," is in the bottom margin of the photograph. Written on the reverse is "H.A.W.P.E."
- A portrait of Sarah B. Bedell, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. Duplicate of 4662. Written on the left side of the original is "Sara E. Bedell."
- A portrait of Ida A. Clarke, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- Lillian M. Potter, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in three corners of the original.
- A portrait of Sarah L. Cole, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Harriet E. Cowles, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. Written in the top right corner is "Hattie Cowles Crescent NY."
- A portrait of Hattie M. Barnett, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "C.A. Howe, 480 Broadway, Albany, N.Y.," is in the bottom margin of the photograph.
- A portrait of Eleanor A. MacNeil, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Belle H. Steedman, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "Rabineau, Albany, N.Y.", is in the bottom margin of the photograph. Written on the reverse is "Hawpe."
- A portrait of Grant Young, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There are small holes, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait in profile of Kate B. Harrington, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Helena M. Buckley, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Mina A. Shepard, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Libbie G. Cornelius, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in three corners of the original.
- A portrait of Ida E. Hobbs, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Margaret B. Imrie, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Isabel C. Maynard, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Louella Measures, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Augustus C. Millin, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Ninetta Belle Collins, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887.
- A portrait of Eliza S. Weston, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Lillian E. Coyne, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original.
- A portrait of Laura V. Curtis, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Sarah B. Bedell, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original. Duplicate of 4661.
- A portrait of Elbert S. Boughton, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Lula E. Burns, New York State College for Teachers, Class of 1887. Written in the top margin is "Lula E. Burns, Delhi NY."
- A portrait of Sarah L. Cole, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887.
- A portrait of Jonathan Hoag, Jr., New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Belle Hoagland, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in three corners of the original.
- A portrait of Jennie Potts, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. Written in the top margin of the original is "Jennie Potts, Upper Red Hook, NY." A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original. Duplicate of 4727.
- A portrait of Elizabeth Shottenkirk, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Stella Cull Beech, who attended the New York State Normal School in 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original.
- A portrait of Ianthe (Effie) E. Post, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "Rabineau, Albany, N.Y.", is in the bottom margin of the photograph.
- A portrait of Jennie Potts, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. Written in the top margin of the original is "Jennie Potts, Upper Red Hook, NY." Duplicate of 4720.
- A portrait of Ella W. Basinger, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. The photographer's stamp, "C.A. Howe, 480 Broadway, Albany, N.Y.," is in the bottom margin of the photograph.
- A portrait of Ella Cornway, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Ida I. George, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in all corners of the original.
- A portrait of Loda E. Pulver, New York State Normal School, Class of 1887. A photographer's stamp for Sterry of Albany, N.Y. is in the lower margin of the original. There is a small hole, possibly from a pin, in each corner of the original.
- A portrait of Jennie C. Godfrey, New York State Normal School, Class of 1888. The photographer's stamp, "Veeder, Albany, N.Y.", is in the bottom margin of the photograph.